Othuke Ajaye

Lagos, Nigeria | ajayeor2kay@gmail.com | +2348184450661 | Linkedin | Portfolio

SUMMARY

A Data Analyst and Scientist with experience analyzing complex data to inform business decisions and drive growth. I provide actionable insights and recommendations to help organizations improve their operations. I'm committed to staying up-to-date with the latest trends and technologies in data analysis and continually seek ways to improve my skills. I also enjoy sharing my knowledge with others, training and mentoring newcomers in data analysis to help them build their skills and confidence.

WORK EXPERIENCE

Revenue Analyst and Reconciliation Specialist at IHS Towers KPMG, Nigeria

May 2023 - Present

- Improved Revenue collection accuracy by 10-15% and reduced discrepancies by 5-10% through in-depth analysis and reconciliation.
- Developed dashboards to track KPIs, increasing report accuracy by 15% and reducing computation time by 40%.
- Automated manual processes using Power Query, saving 50+ hours/quarter (75% reduction in manual effort).

Data Analysis Instructor and Mentor // Erilearn, Lagos, Nigeria

January 2023 - Present

- rained over 100 professionals, providing guidance and mentorship to enhance their data analysis skills.
- Developed comprehensive training materials, customizing content to meet the specific needs of learners, resulting in over 90% satisfaction rate.
- Offered one-on-one tutoring and mentoring, helping newcomers build their skills and confidence in data analysis, with significant improvement in their analytical abilities within 3-6 months.

Data Scientist / Scrum Master // CORONATION

Lagos, Nigeria

June 2021 - May 2023

- Automated performance reports with Power BI, boosting sales, marketing, and customer engagement by 20%, while cutting report generation time by 60%.
- Built predictive models using Python and Azure, reducing complaint resolution time by 30% and enhancing customer segmentation and lead generation.
- Led a cross-functional team of 15+, fostering an agile culture and driving a 40% increase in team productivity, and a 25% reduction in project timelines.

Data Science Intern // EXPLORE AI, South Africa

August 2022 - October 2022

■ Built a Streamlit web app to monitor effluent and wastewater treatment, utilizing Azure Databricks, PySpark, and Amazon S3/EC2 to analyze and visualize large-scale Rand Water datasets in real-time

EDUCATION

DATA SCIENCE

Explore Al Academy, South Africa *Jan 2022 - Oct 2022*

B.Sc Electrical/Electronics Engineering

University of Lagos, Lagos, Nigeria 2014 - 2018

Second Class Upper

Licenses and Certifications

- AWS Certified Cloud Practitioner
- Microsoft Certified: Azure Data Scientist Associate
- Python for Data Science and AI by Coursera and IBM

SKILLS

- Data Analysis: Excel, SQL, Python (NumPy, pandas)
- Data Visualization: Power BI, Tableau, Matplotlib, Seaborn
- Machine learning: TensorFlow, Keras, PyTorch, Scikit-learn
- Big data tools: PySpark, Azure Databricks
- Cloud computing: Azure, AWS
- Agile and Scrum methodologies
- Microsoft Office Suite (Word, PowerPoint)
- Team collaboration: GitHub, Trello, Monday.com
- Communication, problem-solving, and critical thinking